Guide to the Leviticus Lyon PapersJWJ MSS 173
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leviticus Lyon Papers
1905-1948
JWJ MSS 173
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
The Leviticus Lyon papers document the professional and personal activities of the tenor singer, music conductor and choral director. Letters, writings, illustrations and photographs are included in this collection. Correspondence details the life of Leviticus Lyon from childhood to adulthood with personal letters from parents, siblings, and friends including the originally titled "world's fastest human," African American Olympic track star Howard P. Drew. Other correspondence includes letters from blues legend W.C. Handy and prominent Harlem lawyer Hubert T. Delany. The Professional Papers series illustrates Lyon's efforts in establishing the Negro Symphony Orchestra, his participation in the Annual Harlem Music Week, and his work as choral director in the Westchester Negro Choral Union. Personal papers include poems, illustrations, and other writings by Lyon.
Lyon, Leviticus, 1894-1958
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1906-1946. II. Professional Papers, 1918-1948. III. Personal Papers, 1905-1948.
Biographical / Historical
Leviticus Lyon was born on May 29, 1894 in San Francisco, California and spent most of his childhood in Oakland, California. He was born to Elizabeth Garland Lyon and Giraldo Gomez Lyon. Lyon's mother was born in the West Indies (Saint Kitts and Nevis) while his father was born in Guinea-Bissau, West Africa. His father was likely a steward, as his employment in the United States 1900 census is listed as "Stewart" and he frequently discussed life on ships in letters to his son. According to Giraldo Gomez Lyon's personal writings, he immigrated to the United States in 1880 from West Africa and married Elizabeth Garland in 1888. As a teenager, Leviticus Lyon held many jobs including elevator operator at the United States Customs Service in San Francisco, California. Lyon demonstrated his singing talent to officials in the customs department who in turn used their influence to transfer Lyon to work at the New York Customs office in 1919 to assist him in pursuing his musical education. He eventually received a fellowship to study at the Julliard School in 1925. In the course of his career, Lyon became a prominent tenor and choral director, giving performances at Carnegie Hall and St. Marks Methodist Church in Harlem, New York City. Lyon also took leadership positions in New York's music scene, assisting in the formation of the Negro Symphony Orchestra and chairing the Westchester Negro Choral Union. He lived chiefly in New York City until his death in 1958.
Related Materials
Other photographs of Leviticus Lyon can be found in Photographs of Prominent African Americans (JWJ MSS 76).
Scope and Contents
The Leviticus Lyon papers document the professional and personal activities of the tenor singer, music conductor and choral director. Letters, writings, illustrations and photographs are included in this collection. Correspondence details the life of Leviticus Lyon from childhood to adulthood with personal letters from parents, siblings, and friends including the originally titled "world's fastest human," African American Olympic track star Howard P. Drew. Other correspondence includes letters from blues legend W.C. Handy and prominent Harlem lawyer Hubert T. Delany. The Professional Papers series illustrates Lyon's efforts in establishing the Negro Symphony Orchestra, his participation in the Annual Harlem Music Week, and his work as choral director in the Westchester Negro Choral Union. Personal papers include poems, illustrations, and other writings by Lyon.
African American conductors (Music) -- New York (State); Choirs (Music) -- New York (State); Conductors (Music) -- New York (State); Tenors (Singers) -- New York (State); Drawings (visual works); Photographs; Conductors (Music) -- New York (State) -- 20th Century; Delany, Hubert T., 1901-1990; Drew, Howard P.; Handy, W. C. (William Christopher), 1873-1958; Lyon, Leviticus, 1894-1958; Negro Symphony Orchestra; Westchester Negro Choral Union; Annual Harlem Music Week
- Correspondence, 1906–1946; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains both personal and professional correspondence of Leviticus Lyon. Correspondence in this series illustrates Leviticus Lyon's childhood in Oakland and San Fransico, California along with his rise into adulthood and professional career.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - "A" general, 1914–1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anquetil, Raymond, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "B" general, 1914–1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "C" general, 1914–1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Caulkins, Dana, 1938–1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cavallini, Ed., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chorlton, E.A., 1919–1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Benjamin, 1930–1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Davis, Eugene, Circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "D" general, 1917–1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drew, Howard P., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "E" general, 1918–1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "F" general, 1914–1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Forsyth, L.C., 1920–1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "G" general, 1928–1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Garland, Patricia, 1919–1921 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gottsleben, Emil, 1932–1934; Photographs of Lucretia Forsyth (Leviticus Lyon's aunt), the grave of Lucretia Forsyth, and a photograph of Emil Gottsleben (friend of Lucretia Forsyth), are included in this folder. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Green, Robert, 1930–1934 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "H" general, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Handy, W.C. (William Christopher), 1932–1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hernandez, Theodore, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Holloway, Augustus, 1943–1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "I" general, 1918–1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "L" general, 1920–1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Levy, Ferdinand, 1933–1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lyon, Elizabeth G., 1920–1921 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lyon, Giraldo G., 1906–1907 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Lyon, Giraldo G., 1908-1915 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "M" general, 1914–1945 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "N" general, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - National Broadcasting Company, 1933–1934 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Overton, W.S., 1916 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "P" general, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Pitts, Terry, 1938–1939 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "R" general, 1914–1943 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "S" general, 1938–1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "T" general, 1920–1940 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Thomas Music Studio, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Tomlinson, Beatrice W., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Villard, Oswald G., 1918–1919 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "W" general, 1913–1941 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Unidentified, 1920–1936 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
- Professional Papers, 1918–1948; Series II
  The professional papers series documents Leviticus Lyon's efforts in establishing the Negro Symphony Orchestra, his work as choral director in the Westchester Negro Choral Union, and his career as a tenor singer. The series includes memorandums and notes from various organizations such as the Musical Art Group, as well as ephemera including programs from Lyon's singing career.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically with materials within the files arranged chronologically.
  - Aggrey Memorial School, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Annual Harlem Music Week, 1932–1939 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Certificates, resumes and work related materials, 1922–1945 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Dett Musical Club, circa 1920-1946 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Federal Music Project, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Musical Art Group, 1936–1937 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Negro Symphony Orchestra, 1937–1940 (Box 3, Folder 50-53)
  - Negro Symphony Orchestra (oversize), 1939 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - New York Public Library controversy, 1938–1939 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Programs, 1918–1943 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Westchester Negro Choral Union, 1937–1940 (Box 4, Folder 56-60)
  - YMCA, 1933–1948 (Box 4, Folder 61-62)
- Personal Papers, 1905–1942; Series III
  Personal papers include various writings, illustrations and notes by Leviticus Lyon.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically while materials within the folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Addresses and envelopes, Circa 1905-1948 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Birthday card, Circa 1905-1948 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Clippings, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Diary, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Financial documents, 1929–1942 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Government documents, 1917–1920 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Notes, Circa 1905-1948 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Registration and selection for military service, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - School records, 1905–1939 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Writings, 1912–1942 (Box 5, Folder 72-78)
  - Writings of others, Circa 1923 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Writings of others; Sherman Morse clipping (oversize), Circa 1905-1946 (Box 6, Folder 81)